<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Alasdair Sykes</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Alasdair Sykes</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 03 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>soilc.ipcc --- a new R package for soil carbon modelling</title>
      <link>/2021/01/a-new-package-soil-carbon-modelling-in-a-tidyverse-environment.en-us/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/01/a-new-package-soil-carbon-modelling-in-a-tidyverse-environment.en-us/</guid>
      <description>I’ve built a new R package! After nearly a year of rehashing soil carbon modelling code across multiple projects, I finally found the time over the Christmas holidays (when else?) to properly document and contextualise it in a package. I am unapologetically borrowing from the vignette for this new package to form the bulk of this post, since the task of explaining myself intelligently is something I’m lucky to get right once.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Making an API call with R</title>
      <link>/2020/08/making-an-api-call-with-r.en-us/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/08/making-an-api-call-with-r.en-us/</guid>
      <description>A bit of an accidental blog post, this one. My current side project is a Shiny application for estimating solar panel energy generation potential — I’ll be posting plenty about that when it’s more mature — but for now, I found a neat solution that streamlined a small part of that workflow, and I think it might interest some.
In the past, I’ve used spatial data as the building blocks for many of the models I build, and it’s especially pertinent for solar-based models.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>R community links</title>
      <link>/about-alasdair/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/about-alasdair/</guid>
      <description> At one stage I might have said my coding skills were self-taught — but I would strongly revise that to “community-taught” (credit to @EriPDev and @beeonaposy for introducing me to that phrasing in the context of R). In no particular order, here are the blogs of some folks that have helped me along the way:
https://www.thedeltanomics.com  https://scottishsnow.wordpress.com  https://www.r-bloggers.com  https://www.rosannavanhespen.nl  https://www.jumpingrivers.com/blog   </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>R community links</title>
      <link>/r-community-links/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/r-community-links/</guid>
      <description> At one stage I might have said my coding skills were self-taught — but I would strongly revise that to “community-taught” (credit to @EriPDev and @beeonaposy for introducing me to that phrasing in the context of R). In no particular order, here are the blogs of some folks that have helped me along the way:
https://www.thedeltanomics.com  https://scottishsnow.wordpress.com  https://www.r-bloggers.com  https://www.rosannavanhespen.nl  https://www.jumpingrivers.com/blog  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Shiny application showcase</title>
      <link>/shiny-apps/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/shiny-apps/</guid>
      <description>Communicating environmental data science insights via Shiny applications is just about my favourite part of my job. Given the range of contexts and places in which I’m finding myself building apps, I wanted to maintain a page which keeps up-to-date links to the apps next to a record of the context in which they were built. Here they are:
 July 2020 | A decision-support tool for agroforestry policymakers An add-on to an extended modelling project, this app provides an interactive user interface for some of the most interesting data science I’ve done in a while.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Migrating your workflow to R — 6 easy(ish) steps</title>
      <link>/2020/08/migrating-your-workflow-to-r.en-us/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/08/migrating-your-workflow-to-r.en-us/</guid>
      <description>When you look at the online portfolios of established, social-media-present R aficionados, it’s tempting to assume that these folks were born authoring documents in Markdown and piecing together impossibly neat workflows to solve problems that the rest of us are too damn mundane to understand, let alone solve. I think this feeling of comparative inadequacy is particularly prevalent for the occasional useR who comes from a natural science, rather than a computational or mathematical background; most of us from this side of the tracks come to R to solve particular problems in our daily workflow (be it statistical testing, data visualisation, big data handling etc.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PDF scraping with pdftools and purrr</title>
      <link>/2020/07/web-and-pdf-scraping.en-us/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/07/web-and-pdf-scraping.en-us/</guid>
      <description>I thought this would make as good a debut post as any for the new site. Here’s the challenge:
My partner is, like many of us, taking the extended pandemic lockdown/recovery as an opportunity to catch up on some learning — and though I’m lucky enough to be working from home too, I’ve also been looking for ways to feel like I’m doing more than just passing time. As a result, we’ve used our subscriptions budget to sign up to Great Courses Plus, which is essentially geeky version of Netflix, streaming lecture series instead of shows.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>