<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>R Markdown on Alasdair Sykes</title>
    <link>/tags/r-markdown/</link>
    <description>Recent content in R Markdown on Alasdair Sykes</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 04 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/r-markdown/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Migrating your workflow to R --- 6 easy(ish) steps</title>
      <link>/2020/08/migrating-your-workflow-to-r.en-us/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/08/migrating-your-workflow-to-r.en-us/</guid>
      <description>When you look at the online portfolios of established, social-media-present R aficionados, it’s tempting to assume that these folks were born authoring documents in Markdown and piecing together impossibly neat workflows to solve problems that the rest of us are too damn mundane to understand, let alone solve. I think this feeling of comparative inadequacy is particularly prevalent for the occasional useR who comes from a natural science, rather than a computational or mathematical background; most of us from this side of the tracks come to R to solve particular problems in our daily workflow (be it statistical testing, data visualisation, big data handling etc.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PDF scraping with pdftools and purrr</title>
      <link>/2020/07/web-and-pdf-scraping.en-us/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/07/web-and-pdf-scraping.en-us/</guid>
      <description>I thought this would make as good a debut post as any for the new site. Here’s the challenge:
My partner (the wonderful Aisha Josiah) is, like many of us, taking the extended pandemic lockdown/recovery as an opportunity to catch up on some learning — and though I’m lucky enough to be working from home too, I’ve also been looking for ways to feel like I’m doing more than just passing time.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>